Inventory of the Marie Adams papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Marie Adams papers
1887-1950
78076
Adams, Marie, 1891-1976
5 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes (3.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection includes materials relating to Santo Tomás Internment Camp and the Japanese occupation of the Philippines during World War II, in the form of correspondence, propaganda leaflets, printed matter, and memorabilia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1978.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Life without Lipstick by Marie Adams, Hoover Institution Library
Myrene Cassel papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Roger Mansell collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Ann Miller Depew papers, Hoover Institution Archives
William Henry Hastings papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Santo Tomás Internment Camp (Manila, Philippines) Internee Executive Committee issuances, Hoover Institution Archives
Santo Tomás Internment Camp, January 4, 1942-September 27, 1943: typescript, Hoover Institution Archives
Katherine Ream Sobeck papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
1891 Born, Aberdeen, Washington
1936-1941 Executive Secretary of Milwaukee-Downer College, Milwaukee, Wisconsin
1941 Arrives in Manila, Philippines, to work as Field Director of Hospital Services for the American Red Cross
1942-1945 Interned, Santo Tomás Internment Camp (STIC), Philippines
1945 Author, Life Without Lipstick
June 1945 Submits report to the U.S. Office of the Surgeon General on living conditions at STIC following the takeover by the Japanese military authority in 1944
circa 1945 Awarded Bronze Star Medal for service with sick and wounded while interned at STIC
1976 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Having been sent to the Philippines by the American Red Cross in 1941 to work as Field Director for Hospital Services in Manila, Marie Adams found herself among the thousands of American and Allied civilians to be held as prisoners of war at Santo Tomás Internment Camp (STIC). As one of the head nurses at STIC, Adams witnessed first-hand the physical and psychological toll of internment, with circumstances worsening in 1944 after the Japanese military assumed control of operations. The collection is primarily comprised of materials from Adams' time as a prisoner of war and immediately following her release.
Of particular note in the Philippines file is a set of meal tickets and a log of daily meals served at STIC from 1944 to 1945. These materials supplement newsletters and announcements distributed at STIC around this period, providing insight into daily life at the camp. In addition, the series includes printed matter about the Philippine front of World War II, in the form of newspapers, clippings, reports, and studies on the destruction of Manila and the liberation of prisoners of war.
In her time at STIC, Adams wrote a number of poems reflecting on life in the camp, hunger, sickness, and the hope of liberation. These poems were self-published under the title Life Without Lipstick and distributed to friends and family as Christmas presents in 1945. Letters written in response to this book are included in the Letters received series along with letters received by Adams at STIC and congratulatory letters received upon her return home, written by family, close friends, and colleagues from different chapters of the American Red Cross.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 3 series: Philippines file, Letters received, and Memorabilia
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Prisoners of war.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons.; Philippines--History--Japanese occupation, 1942-1945.; Santo Tomas Interment Camp (Manila, Philippines).
Collection Contents
- Philippines file, 1942-1950 (Box 1, 5)
  Includes materials collected from STIC, Japanese and American propaganda materials, and clippings, maps, reports, and studies pertaining to the Philippine front of WWII and the liberation of American prisoners of war.
  Arranged by physical format, then chronologically.
  - Santo Tomás Internment Camp (STIC) materials, 1942-1945 (Folder 1: 1-7)
    - Internal newsletters and publications, 1942-1944 (Folder 1: 1-2)
      Includes issues of STIC Gazette, Internitis, Cavalier, and The Liberator
    - Meal tickets of Otto Joseph Tuschka, 1942-1944 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Notice issued by Japanese commandant, 1943 January (Folder 1: 4)
    - Summary of camp activities and resources, 1943 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Daily log of meals served, 1944-1945 (Folder 1: 6)
      Probably written by Otto or Yetta Tuschka
    - Poems, circa 1944 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Clippings, 1942-1949 (Folder 5: 1-5)
    Includes clippings from Liberty, Life, Readers Digest, San Francisco Chronicle, San Francisco Examiner, Saturday Evening Post, and Woman's Home Companion, relating to the liberation of Manila and returning American soldiers and civilians.
    - 1942 (Folder 5: 1)
    - 1943 (Folder 5: 2)
    - 1945 (Folder 5: 3)
    - 1946 (Folder 5: 4)
    - 1949 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Map of Manila, 1942 (Folder 5: 6)
  - Newspapers, 1942-1945 (Folder 5: 7-8)
    - The Tribune, 1942 April-1943 January (Folder 5: 7)
      Japanese propaganda newspaper
    - Free Philippines, 1945 February-March (Folder 5: 8)
      Newspaper of the U.S. Army published after the liberation of Santo Tomás
  - Program flyer for "Dr. Jay's Medicine Show," Los Baños, 1943 June (Folder 1: 8)
  - Propaganda flyers, Japanese and American, circa 1942 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Propaganda magazine. Shin Seiki. Bagong Araw. New Era. Manila: Philippine Publications, 1942 (Folder 1: 10)
    In English and Tagalog
  - Reports, studies, and other publications, 1944-1950 (Folder 1: 11-15)
    - "Historical Background of International Agreements Relating to Prisoners of War," American National Red Cross, 1944 (Folder 1: 11)
    - Geographical study of Manila issued by U.S. commanders in the Pacific, 1944 (Folder 1: 12)
      Includes printed aerial photographs
    - "Report on the Destruction of Manila and Japanese Atrocities," Office of Resident Commissioner of the Philippines to the U.S., 1945 (Folder 1: 13)
    - The End of the War in the Pacific: Surrender Documents in Facsimile, Washington: United States Government Printing Office, 1945 (Folder 1: 14)
    - War Claims Commission review and directory of paid POWs, 1950 (Folder 1: 15)
- Letters received, 1921-1946 (Box 1-4)
  Includes letters received by Adams from financial institutions, friends, and family.
  Grouped by topic or event, then chronologically.
  - Letters received from banks, insurance companies, and other financial institutions, 1921-1945 (Folder 1: 16-18)
    Includes related statements and receipts
  - Letters of recommendation for employment with American Red Cross, 1937-1941 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Letters received at Santo Tomás, 1941-1944 (Folder 2: 1-9)
    Some letters are postmarked 1943; however, were not actually received by Adams until 1944. Folder titles reflect the date received, as indicated by the creator.
    - 1941-1943 (Folder 2: 1-3)
    - 1944 (Folder 2: 4-9)
      - March-April (Folder 2: 4-5)
      - June (Folder 2: 6)
      - August-September (Folder 2: 7-8)
      - November-December (Folder 2: 9)
  - Christmas cards, 1945 (Folder 2: 10-11)
  - Other greeting cards, 1945 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Letters received upon liberation, 1945-1946 (Folder 2-3)
    - Undated (Folder 2: 13)
    - 1945 (Folder 2-3)
      - January (Folder 2: 14)
      - February (Folder 2: 15)
      - February (contd.) (Folder 3: 1-2)
      - March (Folder 3: 3-5)
      - April (Folder 3: 6)
      - May (Folder 3: 7)
      - June-July (Folder 3: 8)
      - August-September (Folder 3: 9)
      - October (Folder 3: 10)
      - November-December (Folder 3: 11)
    - 1946 January-October (Folder 3: 12)
  - Letters received regarding Life Without Lipstick, 1945-1946 (Folder 4: 1-10)
    - Undated (Folder 4: 1)
    - 1945 (Folder 4: 2-4)
      - March (Folder 4: 2)
      - September-December (Folder 4: 3-4)
    - 1946 (Folder 4: 5-10)
      - January (Folder 4: 5-8)
      - February (Folder 5: 9)
      - March-June (Folder 5: 10)
- Memorabilia, 1887-1940s (Box 6-7)
  Philippine identity papers with metal containers, Japanese Red Cross flag, and wooden sandals.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Philippine identity papers and metal containers, 1887-1898 (Folder 6)
  - Wooden sandals, 1940s (Folder 6)
    Hand-carved sandals with rubber straps, probably worn by an internee at Santo Tomás
  - Description of Japanese Red Cross flag, 1940s (Folder 6)
  - Silk Japanese Red Cross flag, probably 1940s (Folder 7)
    Includes photocopy of description from Box 6.